<rss xmlns:ns0="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Daily Reading</title><link>https://yourusername.github.io/notion-to-rss</link><description>Generated from Notion.</description><item><title> Norbert Elias《The Civilizing Process》 GPT</title><link>https://www.notion.so/1dcd27b98c7f80c28ffbd0af51a0c66e</link><ns0:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norbert Elias’s &lt;strong&gt;The Civilizing Process&lt;/strong&gt; traces how Western European societies evolved from medieval “warrior” cultures into the self‑restrained “civil men” of the 19th century. Drawing on sociogenetic (state formation) and psychogenetic (individual psychology) analyses, Elias shows that as states monopolized violence and networks of interdependence widened, norms of manners, etiquette, and self‑control became internalized. His interdisciplinary methodology—mining literature, memoirs, etiquette manuals, and art—reveals a long‑term decrease in interpersonal violence and the rise of refined social conduct. Although celebrated as a foundational work in historical sociology and criminology, Elias’s thesis has attracted critiques for its Eurocentric focus and for underestimating non‑Western trajectories of civilization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background and Publication History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norbert Elias (1897–1990) was a German sociologist who fled Nazism and completed much of his work in England &lt;a href="https://www.blinkist.com/en/books/the-civilizing-process-en?utm_source=chatgpt.com"&gt;Blinkist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Civilizing Process was first published in German as &lt;em&gt;Über den Prozeß der Zivilisation&lt;/em&gt; in Basel in 1939, but received little attention until its 1969 republication and subsequent English translation &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Civilizing_Process?utm_source=chatgpt.com"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Core Concepts and Arguments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elias introduces a “&lt;strong&gt;double sociogenesis&lt;/strong&gt;,” arguing that state formation has both a &lt;strong&gt;political&lt;/strong&gt; dimension (centralized authority, monopoly of force) and a &lt;strong&gt;mental&lt;/strong&gt; dimension (changes in self‑perception and conduct) &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Civilizing_Process?utm_source=chatgpt.com"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He documents a long‑term trend toward decreasing levels of violence in personal relations, as individuals internalize norms of etiquette and self‑control to align with increasingly complex social networks &lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/social-sciences/civilizing-process?utm_source=chatgpt.com"&gt;科学直接&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://easysociology.com/general-sociology/norbert-eliass-civilizing-process/?utm_source=chatgpt.com"&gt;Easy Sociology&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manners and etiquette manuals, once external rules, become “second nature,” reshaping personalities toward greater &lt;strong&gt;sofistication&lt;/strong&gt; and refinement &lt;a href="https://www.blinkist.com/en/books/the-civilizing-process-en?utm_source=chatgpt.com"&gt;Blinkist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elias builds on Weber’s notion of the state’s “monopoly of the legitimate use of physical force,” showing how privatized violence recedes as centralized authorities regulate conflict, thereby altering citizens’ behavioral repertoires &lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/social-sciences/civilizing-process?utm_source=chatgpt.com"&gt;科学直接&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He posits that individuals develop a collective &lt;strong&gt;habitus&lt;/strong&gt;—a set of embodied dispositions—through ongoing “figurations,” or networks of interdependent relationships. Over centuries, these figurations reshape emotional thresholds and social expectations &lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/333337001_Civilizing_Process?utm_source=chatgpt.com"&gt;ResearchGate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elias’s research spans diaries, literary works, state records, books on courtly etiquette, and visual art. This rich tapestry allows him to chart both sociopolitical structures and minute shifts in comportment &lt;a href="https://academic.oup.com/edited-volume/41333/chapter/352359986?utm_source=chatgpt.com"&gt;OUP Academic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Historical Scope&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His narrative covers approximately 800 AD to 1900 AD, moving from feudal fragmentation to the consolidated nation‑state and modern bourgeois society &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Civilizing_Process?utm_source=chatgpt.com"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact and Reception&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After gaining prominence in the 1970s, &lt;em&gt;The Civilizing Process&lt;/em&gt; became a cornerstone of historical sociology, influencing studies of state formation, habitus, and emotional regulation &lt;a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/0725513616638480?icid=int.sj-full-text.citing-articles.16&amp;utm_source=chatgpt.com"&gt;SAGE Journals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In criminology and penology, scholars have applied Elias’s framework to explain penal reform and the evolution of punishment practices &lt;a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1111/j.1467-954X.2011.01986.x?utm_source=chatgpt.com"&gt;SAGE Journals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Critiques and Debates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elias’s &lt;strong&gt;The Civilizing Process&lt;/strong&gt; remains a seminal work for understanding how macro‑level political changes reconfigure micro‑level behavioral norms over centuries. Its insights into the interplay of power, interdependence, and self‑control continue to inspire and provoke debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;source: &lt;a href="https://www.notion.so/1dcd27b98c7f80c28ffbd0af51a0c66e"&gt;https://www.notion.so/1dcd27b98c7f80c28ffbd0af51a0c66e&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</ns0:encoded><pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 01:49:48 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>